A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Culture Program, Office Files of Alison Bernstein FA1352
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Culture Program, Office Files of Alison Bernstein
1987-1993
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bernstein, Alison R. (1947-2016)
Ford Foundation
FA1352
4.92 Cubic Feet 10 boxes - 9 letter document container and 1 half-letter document container
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Ford Foundation in 2017 and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2017:077, 2017:090, and 2018:037.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Alison Bernstein's correspondence with grantees and colleagues at the Ford Foundation during her time as a program officer and director in the Foundation's Education and Culture program area. The collection also houses reports, correspondence, and office files relating to programs for women, education in Africa, and Ford Foundation Education and Culture programs abroad.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series:
1. Program Officer Files, 1987-1990
2. Director Files, 1991-1993
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Alison Bernstein worked at the Ford Foundation from 1983 until 2010, with a break in the early 1990s to assume the position of Associate Dean of the Faculty at Princeton University. Bernstein started as a program officer in 1983, and she was named director of Education and Culture at the Foundation in 1992. Bernstein was later promoted to vice president of the Ford Foundation's Education, Creativity and Free Expression Program, later called called Creativity and Free Expression. In 2011, Bernstein left the Foundation to become the director of the Institute for Women's Leadership at Rutgers University.
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation and education
- Program Officer Files, 1987-1990; 1
  - Chronological Correspondence Files, 1987 July-1990 February (Box 1, Folder 1-6, Box 2, Folder 7-10)
    Arrangement
    Individual folders arranged in reverse chronological order
  - Alphabetical Correspondence Files A-Z, 1987 April-1990 February (Box 2, Folder 11, Box 3, Folder 12-16, Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Updated Women's Program Forum (WPF) List, 1989 October 13 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Women's Studies/Request for Proposal Letter - Southwest Institute for Research on Women (SIROW), University of Arizona, Tucson, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Questionnaire for Women's Policy Forum (WPF), 1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Domestic Consultant Forms for Helen Cunningham Newbold, S. Zwerling, Ed Hatton for Developing Grant Recommendations, 1990 February 26 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Domestic Consultant Forms - Education and Culture Program Latin American Studies Association Conference, NY, 1989 June 21-23 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Access to Higher Education Program - Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund (MALDEF), 1989 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Hagopian, Harold - Armenian Music Letter, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - National Council for Research on Women - Address List for Women's Centers, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Request for Proposal - Consultants Letter - Panel, 1988 March-May (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Scope and Contents
    RFP sent March 29, 1988 - Review panel for competition to integrate research on minority women into undergraduate liberal arts curriculum
  - Proposal Review Session Letters to Panelists - Minority Women Program, 1988 October 26 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Letters asking Rutgers, Barnard, Columbia, Memphis State, and George Washington University to Resubmit, 1988 November 4 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Letters regarding the Foundation's Minority Women's Studies Program
  - Minority Women's Studies Competition Rejection Letters, Brown, Cincinnati, University of Texas, Smith, 1988 November 15 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Women's Studies/Request for Proposal Letter - Project on Women and Social Change - Smith College, 1988 February (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Women's Studies/ Request for Proposal Letter - Center for Women's Studies - University of Cincinnati, 1988 May 5 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - FY 1988-1989 Budget Projections (Box 5, Folder 33-34)
  - Task Force of Donors to African Education Report on Meeting, Vienna, Austria, 1990 July 23-25 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - A Proposal for the Development of the Association for Examinations and Educational Assessment in East and Southern Africa, Higher Education for Development Co-operation (HEDCO), 1990 March (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Rwanda - Report on School Examination and Educational System, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Using Examinations to Improve Education: A Study in Fourteen African Countries - Synthesis Report - Volume I: Findings and Recommendations (2 copies), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Using Examinations to Improve Education: A Study in Fourteen African Countries - Synthesis Report - Volume II: Costed Action Plans (2 copies), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - PWS Desk File - Special and Miscellaneous Reports (Black and Hispanic Museum/Green), 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folder 40-41)
  - PWS Desk File - Soviet Union Eastern Europe Study Group (Carmichael et al.), 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 42-43, Box 7, Folder 44-45)
- Director Files, 1991-1993; 2
  - Education and Culture Correspondence - Berresford/Gaberman/Jaffe, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Education and Culture Docket Text, 1993 March (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Important Staff Memos for Action (From Susan V. Berresford, Barry D. Gaberman, et al.), 1992 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Trustees Correspondence/Information, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence To/From Director (4 folders), 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 50-53)
  - General Information (Budget/Education and Culture Codes/Staff Assignments), 1992 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - To/From President/Chairman (Franklin Thomas and Edson Spencer), 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence - Interoffice (Other Programs) (2 folders), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 56)
    Governance and Public Policy, Program Related Investments - Miller, Rural Poverty - E. Walter Coward, Urban Poverty R. Curvin
  - 1992 Annual Report - Drafts, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence - Office of Communications, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence - Interoffice, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - US International Affairs Program (USIAP) Administration Grant Correspondence (Maxine Gaddis/Roberta Lynch/Susan Shea/Michele Cole), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Developing Country Program, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Travel Records, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Barry Gaberman Chronological Files (4 folders), 1992 (Box 10, Folder 63-66)
    Folder 62: A-D Folder 63 E-Q Folder 64: R-Z